All right, בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, welcome to the first פרק Perek
of מסכת בבא קמא, Masechet Bava Kamma, דף ב׳. Daf Bet.
Let me say a few words about the בבות Babas and about
בבא קמא Bava Kamma before we start. Number one is that בבא
קמא Bava Kamma means first gate. First gate, middle gate is בבא
מציעא, Bava Metzia, בבא בתרא Bava Batra is last gate. It's really
a way of saying section one, section two, section three. There actually
is another בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, בבא מציעא, Bava Metzia, and בבא
בתרא Bava Batra in ש״ס, Shas, which is in מסכת כלים. Masechet
Keilim. מסכת כלים Masechet Keilim in טהרות, Taharos, I'm sure you've all
learned that, right? So מסכת כלים Masechet Keilim has thirty פרקים Perakim
and it's divided up into three sections of ten פרקים Perakim each.
Here too, the three בבות Babas have ten פרקים Perakim each, equally
divided into three so it's thirty פרקים Perakim and it's pretty clear
that, I mean the גמרא Gemara actually references it, that these initially
really were one מסכת Maseches called מסכת נזיקין. Maseches Nezikin. So we
have סדר נזיקין Seder Nezikin but we had מסכת נזיקין Maseches Nezikin
broken up into section one, section two, section three. Obviously סדר נזיקין
Seder Nezikin constitutes more, it constitutes סנהדרין Sanhedrin and מכות Makkos and
עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah and so on. Which explains another curiosity, which
is as I've told you before, the order of מסכתות Masechtos in
ש״ס Shas is really based on size as defined by number of
פרקים, Perakim, number of chapters. The problem is that each of the
בבות Babas have ten chapters, but סנהדרין Sanhedrin has, how many chapters?
What? Eleven. So why is סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, and not only that, מכות
Makkos only has three chapters and then after מכות Makkos you get
bigger ones like עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. So what's מכות, Makkos, a
small one, doing after סנהדרין Sanhedrin and before עבודה זרה? Avodah Zarah?
So
מכות Makkos was part of סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. So סנהדרין Sanhedrin really had
fourteen chapters. So what's סנהדרין Sanhedrin doing after the בבות? Babas? And
the answer, the בבות Babas had thirty chapters. Okay, so now we've
got that all figured out. Okay, anyway, I know. So a lot
of this is rooted in all of the בבות, Babas, while בבא
בתרא, Bava Batra, a lot of בבא בתרא Bava Batra is Rabbinic
law, and we'll worry about that later, but certainly בבא קמא Bava
Kamma and בבא מציעא Bava Metzia are heavily rooted in פרשת משפטים.
Parshas Mishpatim. And then when you get to סנהדרין Sanhedrin and מכות,
Makkos, that's the other sort of part of משפטים. Mishpatim. That's how
the cases are adjudicated and judged, right? So first you have to
lay out what is the civil law, right, what is that, mostly
it's משפטים, Mishpatim, the civil law, and then you have to deal
with how is it adjudicated? And that's סנהדרין Sanhedrin and מכות Makkos
and how is it judged? And then עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah gets
into other things. Okay? So that's like the basic picture of the
whole thing.
And within that, you know, the רמב״ם Rambam divides it. The רמב״ם
Rambam has two sections of his משנה תורה. Mishneh Torah. One is
called משפטים Mishpatim and the other is called שופטים, Shoftim, right? שופטים
ושוטרים תתן לך. Shoftim V'Shotrim Titein Lecha. Now a lot of things
that סנהדרין Sanhedrin deals with is in פרשת משפטים, Parshas Mishpatim, but
one was the laws and the other are the adjudication, the court
system. So that's the בבות Babas and then סנהדרין Sanhedrin and מכות.
Makkos. Now within בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, of the three, בבא קמא
Bava Kamma is the most coherent. בבא קמא Bava Kamma deals with
really just a few פסוקים Pesukim in פרשת משפטים. Parshas Mishpatim. I
mean, גיטין Gittin dealt with like a total of what, three פסוקים?
Pesukim? Of מסכת גיטין Masechet Gittin was an explication of those three
פסוקים. Pesukim. But anyway, this deals with a few פסוקים Pesukim and
I actually have a very warm spot in my heart for בבא
קמא. Bava Kamma. I really enjoy learning it because it's such a
lovely balance of like מדרשי הלכה, Midrashei Halacha, engaging directly in the
פסוקים Pesukim and then having like you know, these sort of Rabbinic,
you know, סוגיות, Sugyos, classic Talmudic סוגיות. Sugyos. You know, often it's
like something like, okay, so I just got through saying that גיטין
Gittin was all an extrapolation of like three פסוקים Pesukim in the
תורה. Torah. Fine, but right through all of מסכת גיטין Masechet Gittin
you barely ever reference a פסוק, Pasuk, right? Other times like when
we're doing a דרשה Drasha on פסוקים, Pesukim, you do the דרשה
Drasha on the פסוקים Pesukim and there's no real סוגיא Sugya involved.
בבא קמא Bava Kamma is like constantly working with the פסוקים Pesukim
and constantly bringing in the מדרשי הלכה Midrashei Halacha and then extending
and extrapolating and developing that. So it's a really nice sort of
classic, you know, distillation or of תורה שבעל פה Torah She-ba'al Peh
and that sense of the engaging of the פסוקים. Pesukim. So the
first six פרקים Prakim are devoted to what's called נזקי ממון, Nizkei
Mamon, which does not refer to the thing being damaged but the
damaging thing. נזקי ממון Nizkei Mamon is when your property damages. Your
ox goes off and it damages. You were the cause of somebody
else's damage to somebody else's person or property, classically again, as I
said, through your animals, your cow goes off and gores someone and
eats somebody's food and stomps on somebody's vessels. But it could also
be things that are like indirect causation but through some concrete object.
What does that mean? Like indirect means you dig a pit and
something falls into the pit. You light a fire and the fire
spreads. So, you know, you could say the fire is your property
but the pit is your property but really like, I own the
fire? And if I dig the pit in the middle of the
road, it's my property? So there's an interesting conceptual question, do we
categorize those as types of cases of your property damaged, it's a
thing you owned damaged, or do we more categorize it as like
like you brought about the damage, but the normal principle is that
it's גרמא... Grama... indirect causation you're exempt so it's not just that
you brought it about it's that there's through some concrete thing that
you created so that's classic נזקי ממון nizkei mammon there's something concrete
here your cow your well your fire that caused or brought about
damage to somebody else somebody's person or property and therefore you have
a you are liable conceptually
it's an extension of you to some
well we'll talk about there's two ways of thinking about that and
I'll get to that when we get to the first משנה mishna
okay that's the first six chapters are all about are oh and
excuse me within that those chapters is אדם המזיק adam hamazik there's
ממונו המזיק mammono hamazik your property that causes damage and אדם המזיק
adam hamazik you cause damage to somebody else's property okay so that's
also those are the first six chapters you know some degree they're
nicely divided sometimes they're a little bit intertwined but whatever those are
the first six chapters then the remainder of it has to do
more with with again with human acts okay and that's divided into
the following you have the seventh eighth ninth and tenth ones have
to do with גניבה וגזילה gneiva u'gezeila theft and burglary okay a
willful act of stealing somebody else's property either by directly you know
stealing it like you know just out or sneaking like which is
theft or sneaking into their house in the middle of the night
and taking it without their knowledge burglary okay גניבה וגזילה gneiva u'gezeila
that's seven nine and ten what are what does number eight deal
with eight is called החובל hachovel חבלה chavala personal injury so it
is that you damaged another person caused physical injury not to somebody's
property but to their person and obviously there's much greater degrees of
liability when you cause damage to somebody's person so what you'll notice
if you make a matrix about this let's put גניבה וגזילה gneiva
u'gezeila out because that's a separate thing that's an act of stealing
you have I damaged your property that's אדם המזיק adam hamazik that's
somewhere in the first six פרקים prakim I damaged I injured your
person that's חבלה chavala personal injury that's chapter eight my property damages
you that's all called ממונו המזיק mammono hamazik again all the six
פרקים prakim no distinction though between whether my property damages your property
or my property damages your person right and if you think about
it a minute that's like wait that's not exactly fair right at
the end of the day if my ox gores out you know
you know gores somebody's leg and they've now lost use of their
leg shouldn't that be treated differently than if he just damages their
vessels right the same way you do by a human being shouldn't
personal injury also play a factor when it's an animal that does
the damage but we will see that interestingly it really does not
okay so those are the basic types of cases we're dealing with
okay myself or my property
right this would be שור shor or בור bor or אש esh
okay
whatever damages
somebody
else's person
or
let's yeah okay fine person or property okay I have to do
oh I'm sorry I have to go like this person
I don't know if this is making it more confusing or not
is it making it more confusing yes fine forget that okay forget
it made it less confusing for you making it more confusing for
other people what
chapter eight chapter eight means when you cause that you when
you injure somebody else not your property right that's what I was
trying to do on that chart but I see it was
confusing was better without the chart that's what I thought okay anyway
when my person does personal injury to somebody else that's
חבלה chavala when my person does damage to somebody else's property that's
אדם המזיק adam hamazik okay when my property damages somebody else else's
person or property that's ממונו המזיק mammono hamazik so if
you're driving your car you do it or your car so yeah
that's that would be you did it okay because you are directly
manipulating the object that's doing it we'll get to cases like that
but when we say your property damages that means without directly being
manipulated by you okay if I shoot an arrow at somebody right
so then that's like so that would be considered me not my
property yes
you'd also expect a fundamental distinction between your animal and your other
forms of property because the animal has some form of consciousness right
so all of those we're going to get right to in the
first משנה mishna so let's now jump in okay so the first
משנה mishna says ארבעה אבות נזיקין arba'ah avot nezikin
there are four major categories of damage things that a thing I'm
liable for in terms of the damage they cause השור hashor the
ox הבור habor the ditch the well the pit והמבעה vehamav'eh which
is what does that mean debate in the גמרא gemara some say
it means שן shen when my animal eats some say it means
אדם המזיק adam hamazik when a person damages very strange word to
be using וההבער veha'hev'er fire now what What, so these are the
very confusing list. First of all, ox, as we're going to see
in a minute, there are three types of categories in the תורה
Torah when my ox causes damage. One is when it gores somebody,
which is referred to as קרן, Keren, like the horn, the goring.
One is when it tramples on objects, that's called רגל, Regel, okay,
in the Mishnaic Talmudic language. And one when it eats somebody else's,
you know, grain or food or whatever, that's called שן, Shen, the
tooth. All of, so where are all those three different ones? Maybe
they're all meant by the word שור. Shor.
Not if you say מבעה, Maveh,
obviously not if you say מבעה Maveh means eating, right? But okay,
so there, let's assume all three of those are by the word
שור. Shor. So we have all these different types of ways in
which an ox, an ox damages. We have the pit that I
dig, we have a fire. So those are really conceptually different, right?
What is מבעה, Maveh, according to that the only thing מבעה's Maveh
left to be is an אדם המזיק. Adam HaMazik. Okay, but we
will see debates about that. Now,
the other problem is, what is the logic of the order? So
רש"י Rashi says, if you take a look at the, at correct
רש"י, Rashi, I just have to share this is such a great
little חידוש Chiddush here, not of mine, of a ראשון. Rishon. שור
ובור, Shor VaBor, רש"י Rashi says, כסדר שכתובים בפרשה סדרן במשנה. Keseder
she'ketuvim ba'parsha sidran ba'mishna. The פרשה ראשונה Parsha Rishona נאמרה בשור, ne'emra
be'shor, שניה בבור. shniya be'bor.
רש"י Rashi says this is the order that they appear in פרשת
משפטים. Parshat Mishpatim. תוספות Tosafot says this is not the order that
they appear in פרשת משפטים, Parshat Mishpatim, okay? I won't walk you
through the תוספות, Tosafot, but based on how you interpret what these
things mean, תוספות Tosafot says this is not the order they appear
in פרשת משפטים. Parshat Mishpatim. How can they have that debate? This
is... I don't know. This is not the order they appear in
פרשת משפטים. Parshat Mishpatim. So תוספות Tosafot does somersaults trying to figure
out what the logic of the order is. The absolute best answer,
which is the absolute right answer, no question about it, is from
the רבנו פרץ. Rabbeinu Peretz. And what he says is, the reason
it's in this order is not because of any order in the
פסוקים Psukim or any logical order, it's because this is a good
mnemonic in order to remember it when you're teaching it orally: שור
בור מבעה הבער. Shor Bor Maveh Hev'er. Okay? It's like phonetically, it
almost rhymes, they go together. That also explains why they picked a
weird word for מבעה. Maveh. Whatever מבעה Maveh means, the answer is
the reason they picked the word because it rhymes with הבער Hev'er
or it sounds like הבער. Hev'er. Okay? So anyways, those are the
four categories. Now, let's see where the משנה Mishna goes with this.
It's very interesting, I just mentioned how the whole מסכת Masechet deals
with מדרשי הלכה. Midrashei Halacha. The first משנה Mishna pretty much opens
up with מדרשי הלכה. Midrashei Halacha. So let's look at the
משנה. Mishna. לא הרי השור כהרי המבעה ולא הרי המבעה כהרי השור.
Lo ha'rei ha'shor ke'harei ha'maveh ve'lo ha'rei ha'maveh ke'harei ha'shor. The characteristics
of the שור Shor are not like that of מבעה. Maveh. We
will assume for now, let's say for simplicity sake, מבעה Maveh is
אדם המזיק. Adam HaMazik. Okay, and the characteristics of מבעה, Maveh, let's
say אדם המזיק, Adam HaMazik, is not like that of the ox.
Meaning there are way, reasons which if I just had one of
them, I could not have inferred that the other one is liable,
okay? This one has certain stringent characteristics which it, which explain why
you're liable, but the other one doesn't have and vice versa. So
any one by themselves I would not have been able to infer
one from the other. Okay, now, but now I have both of
them. Okay, even if I have both of them, can I generalize
to all cases that you're liable when your property does damage? No.
ולא זה וזה שיש בהן רוח חיים. Velo zeh va'zeh she'yesh bahen
ruach chayim. Both of those, שור Shor and מבעה, Maveh, are living
things. Either one is your goring animal and one is your eating
animal, or one is your animal and one is yourself. But those
are living beings, there you go, Dov, the point you made, like
sort of conscious living beings, and maybe that's a special reason to
be obligated for, and I could not have inferred from that to
apply it כהרי האש, ke'harei ha'esh, like fire. Fire's inanimate, and maybe
for its, if it's inanimate maybe there's less reason to be liable.
Now, why there's less reason I'll get to. But anyway, clearly it's
a different type of a thing. Fire is different than your ox.
Okay, now, שאין בהן רוח חיים, she'ein bahen ruach chayim, fire does
not have the, is not, does not have a spirit of life,
is not a living thing. Now, how about if I just had
the ox with its variations, maybe the human being, maybe fire, could
I have inferred from that the pit? What do you guys think?
If I knew you were liable for your ox, for yourself, and
for your fire, could I have inferred you're liable for your pit?
Why?
It doesn't move.
All these things move, they go out and do acts of damage
to other people. My fire burnt somebody else. My ox gored somebody
else. They go out and they damage and they do acts. Other
people come to my pit and fall in my pit, right? Maybe
I'm not as liable for that. Okay?
Why does it keep repeating הרי, harei, like כהרי האש? ke'harei ha'esh?
That's,
that's just the idiomatic expression, it means it doesn't have the same
characteristics, okay? So you're saying some character, the relevant characteristics is sort
of what it means. Okay. ולא זה וזה שדרכן לילך ולהזיק, Velo
zeh va'zeh she'darkan leilech u'lehazik, and these are not, all of these
that have the way of going out and damaging are not כהרי
הבור, ke'harei ha'bor, like the. לא זה כזה שדרכן לילך ולהזיק Lo
zeh k'zeh she'darkan leilech lehazik and these are not all of these
which have the way of going out and damaging are not כהרי
הבור Ka'harei habor like the pit שאין דרכו לילך ולהזיק She'ein darko
leilech lehazik that doesn't go out and do damage. Okay, so I
have all of these different things and as many of you know
from this לא הרי זה כהרי זה Lo harei zeh ka'harei zeh
ולא הרי זה כהרי זה, Velo harei zeh ka'harei zeh, it ends
with הצד השוה שבהן, Hatzad hashaveh shebahen, the common side, the common
denominator, meaning one of them does not, you cannot learn out the
other one. If I have all of them, I can infer the
principle that guides all of them and then I can abstract and
apply that principle to cases that don't exactly fit into any one
of these four categories. Great! So this opening משנה Mishna is going
to tell us the secret. It's going to tell us, I'm serious,
you know, it's like when do you get a משנה Mishna like
this that really starts at the beginning? Okay, I mean, okay, lays
out some basic cases in the תורה Torah and tells you here
is the operating principle, here is what is the basis of why
you're liable and presumably that you cannot now apply to any case.
So let's
see what the answer to the question is. Okay, הצד השוה שבהן,
Hatzad hashaveh shebahen, the common side denominator, שדרכן להזיק, she'darkan lehazik, it
is their propensity to damage, not לילך ולהזיק, leilech lehazik, to go
out and actively do damage to somebody else, but they have a
propensity to cause damage. Okay,
ושמירתן עליך, ushmiratan alecha, and you have a responsibility to watch them,
make sure that that doesn't happen.
וכשהזיק, uch'shehizik, and when they do damage, חב המזיק לשלם תשלומי נזק,
chav hamazik leshalem tashlumei nezek, the damager, which is you, I mean,
you're not necessarily the מזיק, mazik, you're the owner of the property,
but it's interesting it's calling you the מזיק, mazik, you become liable
to pay compensation for the damage במיטב הארץ. b'meitav ha'aretz. And if
you're paying not with cash, but with land, you have to pay
with grade A land. So that is adding in a lot of
things, right? It's telling you number one, what is the general rule,
presumably applies to things that don't fall under those categories. Also it's
telling you what the nature of the, of the payment is, if
it's going to be land it has to be the best land.
But there's also a really important question about how to parse this.
How do you parse the ו vav of ושמירתן עליך? ushmiratan alecha?
It's like by, you know, יעקב Yaakov where he makes a נדר.
neder. He says, אם יהיה אלהים עמדי ושמרני בדרך הזה אשר אנכי
הולך והיה ה' לי לאלהים והאבן הזאת אשר שמתי מצבה יהיה בית
אלהים. im yihyeh Elokim imadi ushmarani baderech hazeh asher anochi holech vehayah
Hashem li leilokim veha'even hazot asher samti matzeivah yihyeh beit Elokim. What
is his condition and what is his, what's he going to do?
Is it, if God serves for me as a God, then I'll
make this as a מזבח? mizbeach? Or is it, if God does
all of this for me, then He'll be my God, and otherwise
He won't be my God? Right? Where do you exactly transition from
the condition to the actual consequence? So here too it's a very
interesting question with ושמירתן עליך. ushmiratan alecha. Is ושמירתן עליך ushmiratan alecha
characterizing the types of things you will be liable for? Those things
that you have an obligation to watch are the things you will
be liable for, which of course begs the question. What question does
it beg? Does it? It's possible.
Yes, which
things do I have an obligation to watch, right? Okay, or do
you say,
we just said the things you have an obligation to watch yourself,
you
have, no, but we're abstracting it, you want to apply it beyond
these cases. So is it those that have a propensity to damage
and you have an obligation to watch are the things you're liable
for if they go out and damage? Or, those things that have
a propensity to damage, you have an obligation to watch them and
if you don't watch then you're going to be liable to pay.
Of course the question is, wait, but not everything that has a
propensity to damage. I don't have an obligation to watch your ox,
I don't have an obligation to watch an ownerless ox. So there's
still a question that needs to be answered, but it's very interesting
whether ושמירתן עליך ushmiratan alecha is a consequence and we first define
a basic relationship which imposes upon you an obligation to watch and
liability, or no, does it start with identifying things that you're liable
to watch and then we can talk about the liability. Okay? So
very interesting. One other thing to say about this broad case, or
two other things to say about this broad principle. Number one is
that this gets to the question Rabbi Dov was asking, which is
how do you conceptualize, this is really key, this is going to
be a key guiding question for the whole next six פרקים, prakim,
so pay attention. I'm serious. Here is, how do you conceptualize why
am I liable? Am I liable because it's my fault? I should
have watched my animal, I shouldn't have dug that pit, I shouldn't
have lit that fire and I shouldn't have, if I was going
to I needed to have watched it. It's my fault. Okay, basically
a type of פשיעה, p'shiah, I am to blame. Alright, then we
just identify what are the things that you have an obligation to
that you are to blame for. If it's your ox you should
be watching it, if it's your fire you should be watching it,
a pit you shouldn't be digging it in the middle of the
street. But basically the answer is it's my fault. Okay, that's one
way of conceptualizing it. Alright? The other way of conceptualizing it, I
don't care if it's my fault or not. My thing did it.
My kid goes into the store and he breaks, you know, the
vases there. It doesn't matter if I was attending to some emergency
and I was, I had, I was אנוס onus and I couldn't
be watching my kid, my kid
broke. If my property causes damage, I've got to pay for it.
Okay, so one of them, the first
approach, it's my fault, seems much strongly emphasized by this משנה. Mishna.
It speaks about my obligation to watch, it says that, you know,
it says that I cause me the מזיק, mazik, if they damage
the מזיק, mazik, I'm called the
מזיק, mazik, okay, so cause from my obligation and I become obligated,
you know, and I'm the מזיק, mazik, very much emphasizes it's like
it's my fault, I'm to blame. All right, another way of talking
about it is this idea that no, it's just my property, I
it's like liability rather than fault, okay, absolute liability. And that's normally
framed in the sort of אחרוניש achronish literature as just ממון המזיק.
mamon hamazik. The phrase I used before ממון המזיק, mamon hamazik, it's
not my פשיעה, pshia, my negligence, it's my property did it and
therefore I pay for it. Okay, so there you see how well...
Well, the question is everybody agrees there are cases I'm exempt, like
if I watched it, my animal, I'm exempt. But how do you
conceptualize it? Do you conceptualize it you really should be liable, but
you know what, since you tried, we'll we'll we'll let you off,
okay, but but there starts with a fundamental approach to liability. Or
do you say, of course you're not liable, you had no fault,
you did what you're supposed to be. So how what type of
watching gets me off,
right, makes a big difference if I start with a presumption of
liability or I start with with a presumption that you're only going
to be, you know, obligated once you are negligent. Yes, Rabbi Dov.
Just to suggest another overarching thing, maybe you want to put this
in a different point, but the מיטב הארץ, meitav haaretz, this categorization
of liability.
So we're going to have a whole section in the גמרא Gemara
that's going to be about מיטב, meitav, okay, so that's going to
be like to to so we will get back to that, yeah.
Is it peculiar to include the בור bor as דרכו להזיק? darko
lehazik?
It's the one
thing that's not ambulatory, it doesn't... Well, that's it's not לילך ולהזיק,
leileich ulehazik, so להזיק דרכו lehazik darko here means it has a
propensity to cause damage, okay, it's dangerous, exactly, exactly. In a way
it's more דרכו להזיק, darko lehazik, maybe your phrase isn't the להזיק
lehazik which sounds like an active act of damaging, okay, but it
means to bring about damage.
People aren't necessarily דרכו להזיק, darko lehazik, well,
right, that's we're going to be seeing that. Great, let's look at
the גמרא. Gemara. מדקתני אבות מכלל דאיכא תולדות, Midektani avos michlal d'ika
toldos,
since it says there are four fathers categories, it means that there
are also descendants, children, there are things that are sub-things within the
categories, okay. תולדותיהן כיוצא בהן או לאו כיוצא בהן? Toldoseihen k'yotzei bahen
o lav k'yotzei bahen?
Are their descendants like them or not like them? Now why would
I have thought that they wouldn't be? Isn't the whole idea of
making categories to say that these things therefore follow the same rules?
So the גמרא Gemara says, look, גבי שבת תנן, gabi shabbos tnan,
by Shabbos we taught, אבות מלאכות ארבעים חסר אחת, avos melachos arba'im
chaser achas, there are thirty-nine
מלאכות, melachos, מכלל דאיכא תולדות, michlal d'ika toldos, the fact that it
calls it thirty-nine categories or fathers means that there are descendants, right,
one of the major categories is is cooking,
a descendant would be frying or baking, actually technically it's baking and
cooking is a descendant. Okay, anyway, right, there's all these sub-things that
are part of the that are the תולדות. toldos. So are now
the הלכה halacha is that the תולדות toldos have the same law
as the אבות. avos. לא שנא אב חטאת ולא שנא תולדה חטאת,
lo shna av chatas velo shna toldah chatas, if you do it
בשוגג, beshogeg, whether you're doing the אב, av, whether you're doing the
תולדה, toldah, right, whether you are I don't know harvesting wheat or
picking apples, you are either way violating Shabbos דאורייתא, d'oraisa, a מלאכה
melacha and you have to bring a חטאת chatas if you did
it בשוגג, beshogeg, a sin offering.
What the consequences of the act are the same.
Right, oh yeah, that's what כיוצא בהן k'yotzei bahen means as opposed
to what, how do the nature as opposed to the things that
we characterize in it do they have the same character? Right, so
that's the point and it'll be a little tricky in a minute,
but you are right, the presumption is something only gets called a
תולדה toldah because it shares relevant characteristics, so the otherwise if it
was if it had a different characteristics it wouldn't be a תולדה
toldah and then the question is, but are the laws the same?
Correct. So, okay, so either way you have a חטאת. chatas. לא
שנא אב סקילה ולא שנא תולדה סקילה, lo shna av skila velo
shna toldah skila, and if you do it willfully, so whether it's
the father or the child, you will get you will get stoned.
Okay, if that's true, who needs the categorization? ומאי איכא בין אב
לתולדה, Uma'i ika bein av letoldah, is there any difference between the
אב av and the תולדה? toldah? So yes, נפקא מינה, nafkaminei, here's
the difference, דאילו עבד שתי אבות בהדי הדדי, d'ilu avid shtei avos
bahadi hadadei, if you did two אבות avos מלאכה melacha at the
same time, okay, presumably of different מלאכות, melachos, אינמי שתי תולדות בהדי
הדדי, Inami shtei toldos bahadi hadadei, or two תולדות toldos at the
same time, again presumably of different מלאכות, melachos, in that case מחייב
אחדא ואחדא, mechayiv achada vechada, you would have to bring a different
קרבן korban for each one. We can't kill you twice, but if
it's about קרבנות, korbanos, you'd have to bring a different קרבן korban
for each
one, okay, דאילו עבד אב ותולדה דידיה... d'ilu avid av vetoldah dideih...
forgetfulness. You forgot it was שבת. Shabbos. Okay, you forgot these things
were אסור assur and you did these acts, okay, לא מחייב אלא
חדא. lo mechayev ella chada. You'd only bring one. Now I did
in a parenthetically say something as I was reading you presumably תולדות
toldos of different אבות avos
because there's two ways of conceptualizing this. The way we basically what
we basically say להלכה l'halacha is anytime you do multiple things that
fall into the same category, you only בשוגג beshogeg in one state
of forgetfulness, you're only going to bring one קרבן. korban. So if
I cook twice, I bring one קרבן. korban. If I bake and
I fry, I bring one קרבן. korban. If I cook and I
bake, I bring they're all in the same category. They're all variations
of the theme, of the theme. However, you could have read the
גמרא Gemara a little different. You could read the גמרא Gemara that
because something is a תולדה tolada it gets it gets like it
gets shadowed over in the presence of its אב. av. So if
you have an אב av and a תולדה, tolada, it's not because
they're in the same category. The תולדה tolada is discounted or like
whatever bracketed, it doesn't carry its own weight in the presence of
its אב. av. But if you have two אבות avos but if
you cook and cook or you bake or you fry and fry,
right, then one doesn't overwhelm the other and then you would be
חייב chayav twice. It's only when you have the big thing and
the small thing as it were that then they get conflated. Anyway,
that's not the way you see how you could read that into
the גמרא. Gemara. שניא מדאבוה מניה. shanya mi'd'avuh mineih. Something like that
although they're of equal weight. Anyway, you're not seeing the two different
ways to read the גמרא? Gemara?
But you see if you fry and fry, I mean different form
of frying?
No, let's say I do the same thing twice, okay, two תולדות,
toldos, right, you could read the גמרא Gemara to say that even
if I do two תולדות.
toldos. Is this a different ones?
No, just they're both אב ואב, av v'av, תולדה ותולדה. tolada v'tolada.
The only thing the גמרא Gemara excludes from two קרבנות korbanos is
an אב av and its תולדה. tolada. So you could say any
other matching of two things, they don't overwhelm things of equal weights
or an אב av and a different תולדה. tolada. The only thing
that sort of overshadows is an אב av in the presence of
its own תולדה. tolada. All right, so but anyway, we don't say
that. We basically say anytime something falls into one category, multiple אבות,
avos, multiple תולדות, toldos, whatever, if it's all in one category, it's
one קרבן. korban. Different categories for different קרבנות. korbanos. Yes.
If you do fry and then you fry again, would you need
to have a warning for the second?
If it's במזיד, b'meizid, but we're talking about בשוגג. b'shogeg. Okay. Right,
but it's bizarre to think that anyway
that even בשוגג b'shogeg you could do two. So anyway there's different
ways to say what I just said, but I don't want to
go any further. Okay, but bottom line is the purpose of categorizing
אב av and תולדה tolada is to say that when it falls
within one category, everything that falls in one category is going to
bring be one קרבן. korban. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says, ולרבי
אליעזר, u'l'Rabbi Eliezer, but it's not really a different הלכה. halacha. It's
not תולדות toldos are treated less weightily or differently, it's just when
they're all in the same category, it's only going to be one
קרבן. korban. ולרבי אליעזר דמחייב אתולדה במקום אב. u'l'Rabbi Eliezer d'mechayev a'tolada
bimkom av. Now רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says
that if you do an אב av with its תולדה, tolada, you
actually bring two קרבנות. korbanos. So according to that, אמאי קרי ליה
אב ואמאי קרי ליה תולדה? amai kari leih av v'amai kari leih
tolada? Why is it called an אב av and a תולדה? tolada?
So the גמרא Gemara says, הך דהוי במשכן חשיבא קרי ליה אב.
hach d'havah b'mishkan chashiva kari leih av. That that was in the
משכן Mishkan in terms of the acts that were done in the
building of the משכן, Mishkan, they and that were important, those are
called the אב. av. הך דלא הוי במשכן חשיבא, hach d'lo havah
b'mishkan chashiva, those that were not important and were not in the
משכן Mishkan and important, it's a question of how to parse it,
I'll get back to
that, קרי ליה תולדה. kari leih tolada. Which basically means, one minute,
basically means there's no halachic relevance of calling it anything. It's just
a way of labeling and categorizing, but at the end of the
day, you could give me a list of a thousand things that
are אסור assur on שבת Shabbos without any categories and it would
not matter whether it was a thousand דאורייתא d'oraysa מלאכות melachos on
שבת Shabbos or whether it was thirty-nine and categorizing it the way
you did. None of that. It's all just a way of identifying
which are the things that are derived from which started at the
משכן, Mishkan, which are the derived, a way of organizing it, but
there's no halachic meaning at all to that. Now, what does it
mean במשכן חשיבא? b'mishkan chashiva? Does it mean anything that was in
the משכן Mishkan is important and therefore is called an אב av
and anything that wasn't in the משכן Mishkan is not important? Or
does it mean you have to have two characteristics: it was in
the משכן Mishkan and it was important? A lot of things they
did in the משכן Mishkan that were not important enough to raise
to the level of an אב, av, right? I mean, you know,
if they shined a piece of metal, that's not a מלאכה, melacha,
right? It's only things that are identified within the things of the
משכן, Mishkan, we have to identify which are the ones that are
really of creative significance. Okay. Anyway, so that's an interesting question about
how do you identify what the אבות מלאכות avos melachos are. But
anyway, according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer it's just a way of
labeling and categorizing, no נפקא מינה nafka mina at all. But even
according to the to our general approach, it's not that a תולדה
tolada has a different דין, din, it's just that when some things
of a same category come Together, they're treated differently.
Are you saying חשיבות Chashivus is important, or is it חשוב Chashuv
in that way, or is it counted? Because that's what I was
thinking.
Identify an action in that context.
Yeah, so I think that it is read both ways, תוספות Tosafos
tends to read חשיבה Chashiva as חשוב, Chashuv, as important, but you
could say anything that wasn't in the משכן Mishkan is חשיבה, Chashiva,
is either important or is
counted, but then it would just be חשיבה, Chashiva, I don't know,
the grammar is funny. Anyway, but yes, you could read it that
way. Okay, so that's שבת. Shabbos. גבי טומאה תנן, Gabei tuma tenan,
now by טומאה Tuma we teach, אבות הטומאות השרץ ושכבת זרע וטמא
מת, Avos hatumos hasheretz v'hashichvas zera utmei meis,
a source of טומאה, Tuma, the primary source of טומאה, Tuma, something
that is not a derivation but is the primary source. So what's
a primary source? So well obviously the first thing we think of
is a human corpse. Okay, but we'll get to that. But you
have a dead rodent. Okay, or you can think about a שרץ.
Sheretz. Or you can think or you can think about a נבילה,
Neveila, another like a dead animal. Or שכבת זרע, Shichvas zera, like
what do you call it, semen. You could also talk about people
that are primary source. A מצורע, Metzora, a נדה, Nida, a זבה,
Zavah, a זב. Zav. Okay, all these things although these are presumably
talking about now the interesting thing that includes in this is טמא
מת. Tmei meis. טמא מת Tmei meis is not a מת. Meis.
טמא מת Tmei meis is a person who came in contact with
a מת. Meis. Technically speaking that should be a תולדה Toldah because
it's a derivative טומאה. Tuma. He gets it by contact but because
in the תורה Torah it's clear that that person is טמא Tamei
for seven days and we know that and we sort of generally
start with a presumption here and that well we'll see in a
minute. We know from other הלכות Halachos that that person operates with
the same weight. His טומאה Tuma carries the same weight as something
like a dead rat or something like a נדה, Nida, the person
who touched the מת Meis or a זב. Zav. Okay, so therefore
it's not a rat actually it's not one of the שרצים. Sheratzim.
But anyway, okay. So therefore even though it's derivative we call him
an אב הטומאה. Av hatuma. So then what do we call the
מת? Meis? אבי
אבות הטומאה, Avi avos hatuma, the granddaddy of טומאה. Tuma. Okay, so
it's like what is it like the zeroth law of thermodynamics? Okay,
so these are all the אבות Avos but there's a zeroth law
there's the מת Meis itself. Okay, so technically he's derivative but he's
given the status of אב הטומאה Av hatuma because it carries the
same weight as everything else in the תורה Torah other than a
מת Meis that's a primary source of טומאה. Tuma. So that's the
אב הטומאה, Av hatuma, the primary source. תולדותיהן לאו כיוצא בהן, Toldosehen
lav k'yotzei bahen, and their derivatives don't have the same הלכה. Halacha.
דאילו אב מטמא אדם וכלים, De'ilu av mitamei adam v'keilim, an
אב Av if they touch a person or they touch vessels they
make it טמא. Tamei. The נבילה, Neveila, the טמא מת Tmei meis
and so on. Okay the זב, Zav, דאילו תולדותיהן, De'ilu toldosehen, תולדות,
Toldos, but if you have something that touched the אב Av and
is a derivative it's what we call a ראשון. Rishon. א ראשון
A rishon means a first generation derivative. There's the אב הטומאה Av
hatuma which is the source and then there's the ראשון Rishon the
first generation derivative, the שני Sheni is the second generation derivative. So
if something is a ראשון Rishon is a derivative in that case,
okay, דאילו תולדות אוכלין ומשקין מטמא. De'ilu toldos ochlin umashkin mitamei. So
if I went if if what? If he touched the טמא מת?
Tmei meis?
If I touched the טמא מת Tmei meis or I touched the
שרץ, Sheretz, I become טמא, Tamei, I'm a ראשון. Rishon. I now
if I touch food or vessels I will make them טמא. Tamei.
Okay but אדם וכלים לא מטמא, Adam u'keilim lo mitamei, I cannot
make I'm sorry I said did I say vessels? I meant to
say food. If I touch food I will make it טמא Tamei
but if I touch a person or vessels לא מטמא Lo mitamei
I cannot. So the only way a person or vessels can become
טמא Tamei is in direct contact with the אב. Av. If a
derivative can only affect food. Did I say food before? The only
way a human or vessel can be טמא Tamei is in direct
contact with the אב. Av. If you're dealing with a derivative טומאה
Tuma that can only be מטמא Mitamei food. So תולדותיהן לאו כיוצא
בהן. Toldosehen lav k'yotzei bahen. Now הכא מאי? Hacha mai? Here what's
the story? Are the תולדות Toldos like it or not like it?
Now the obvious point to say here right away is that is
a complete different use of the word אב Av and תולדה. Toldah.
One is a primary category a way of labeling the category of
which things are conceptually derivative but ultimately what we're saying is that
shares characteristics and should be categorized in the same way. One might
have appeared in the תורה Torah or in the משנה. Mishnah. These
other things okay it's not my ox that gores it's my bee
that stings or it's my dog that bites but nevertheless these are
basically concept like they're not the same concrete case but but they're
basically saying they share the relevant characteristics and they're put in the
same category. Right as opposed to this the case of טומאה Tuma
where it's the point is that it's the actual טומאה Tuma that
is one step derived. The actual we're not talking about does it
share characteristics? It's the thing itself that has actually been derived you
know that that has transferred and been derived. So the obvious point
would be of course here to be כיוצא בהן. K'yotzei bahen. It
should be like שבת. Shabbos. You put it in the same category
and then it has the same הלכות. Halachos. Okay so the question
seems pretty obvious where it's headed. Now the other thing so let's
see what the גמרא Gemara says. Some are like them, some are
not like the אבות, avot, which is like okay, that was a
very curious answer, you care to tell us which? So now what
the גמרא's Gemara going to do is it's going to go on
for about two דפין dappein going through all of the אבות נזיקין
avos nezikin and identifying whether and talking about their תולדות, toldos, talking
about how we categorize what's an אב, av, you know, what defines
this category and what's in the category and what are the תולדות,
toldos, and then discussing what are the הלכות halachos that apply to
the category and then looking at whether those הלכות halachos are the
same as with the תולדות toldos as with the אב. av. In
other words, it is a great little opening survey and introduction to
the next six פרקים. prakim. You're going to be introduced to all
of the major categories, their basic definitions and characteristics, and what are
the laws that apply to them, all in the service of answering
the question of whether תולדות toldos are כיוצא בהן. kiyotzei bahem. So
obviously, the point I'm making is it's not really in the service
of that, it's the opposite, and this is a classic opening סוגיא
sugya of a מסכתא masechta where basically it asks a question which
isn't so much of a question, okay, but it's a way of
getting you into material later into the מסכתא. masechta. All right. So
is all of that going to be in service of comparing the
terminology of אבות avos and תולדות toldos for טומאה tumah to— No,
we're dropping we completely ignore טומאה tumah and שבת. Shabbos. That was
just a setup. From here on in we're just going to be
saying what are the אבות, avos, what are their תולדות, toldos, do
the תולדות... toldos... it's really an explication of רב פפא'ס Rav Pappa's
statement. Do the תולדות toldos follow the same rule as the אבות
avot or not follow the same rule of the אבות? avot? Okay.
The שבת Shabbos and טומאה tumah was just a way to set
to raise the question. It really... and that's another point by the
way that if you actually ask what was the original construct of
this פרק perek or whatever this of this סוגיא, sugya, probably it
started with you had the משנה mishna and you had the statement
of רב פפא. Rav Pappa. Exactly. You have the משנה mishna and
right after the משנה mishna said אבות מלאכות... avos melachos... no, אבות
נזיקין, avos nezikin, רב פפא Rav Pappa said יש כיוצא בהן ויש
לאו כיוצא בהן. yesh kiyotzei bahem v'yesh lav kiyotzei bahem. But
the גמרא Gemara went back and said oh let's explain to you
where רב פפא'ס Rav Pappa's coming from because we have other cases
of אבות avot and תולדות toldot and some are כיוצא kiyotzei and
some are not כיוצא kiyotzei and רב פפא Rav Pappa wanted to
ask this question do we assume that the תולדות toldos are כיוצא
kiyotzei or not. So now we got to רב פפא. Rav Pappa.
רב פפא'ס Rav Pappa's question clearly came before the סתם stam that
was put in to set up the question, which is why we're
never going to talk about שבת Shabbos and טומאה tumah after this.
Okay. Now we're just going to talk about is it כיוצא? kiyotzei?
What is the אב? av? What are the תולדות? toldos? Are they
כיוצא? kiyotzei? Which is a perfect opening סוגיא sugya to give us
a survey of what are all of the different types of אבות
נזיקין avos nezikin that we're going to be dealing with. What does
the גמרא Gemara mean precisely when they say כיוצא בהן? kiyotzei bahen?
Does it follow the same הלכות? halachos? In what way? Okay, so
that in what way gets to the point I was going to
make on the משנה mishna but I'll make it now, which is,
and this is another big question about the first six פרקים prakim
and certainly the first פרק. perek. When the משנה mishna ended with
saying הצד השוה שבהן, hatzad hashaveh shebahen, once we have a common
rule, a common denominator, and a general rule, do we need the
categories anymore? Who needs to call something a קרן keren or a
שן shein or a רגל regel or a בור bor or an
אש? esh? It's all one rule. It's very simple. Okay? Were you
obligated to watch it? Yes. Okay, so then you're liable for damages.
Like okay, we can just close the whole מסכתא. masechta. That's six
פרקים prakim we just covered. Okay, so the answer is that we
can't say that because each one of those categories has special rules
attached to them. If it's an ox that gores, you only pay
half the first three times. If it's an animal that tramples or
eats, you're exempt if it does it in the public domain, in
רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. If it's a well, you're exempt for vessels
that break in a well. I mean right. שור ולא אדם חמור
ולא כלים. shor v'lo adam chamor v'lo kelim. Right. Okay. If it's
fire, you're exempt if something was buried under a haystack. Okay, so
it really it really does matter. These four categories have very special
הלכות. halachos. So then if that's true, who needs the common rule?
So maybe there's both things going on. If we can put you
into one of those four categories, then you get the special הלכה
halacha of those four. If we can't put you in one of
those four, then you get this catch-all, oh well it's your property
and you were obligated to watch and you're going to pay. Okay,
so there's like a catch-all rule and then there's a specific category
rule. So that's the question of how those two relate. All right.
But that's why we want to know כיוצא בהן kiyotzei bahen or
לא כיוצא בהן, lo kiyotzei bahen, right? So the question would be,
if you have a תולדה toldah of קרן, keren, are you going
to get pay half for the first three times or not? Does
it have those special הלכות halachos of קרן keren or not? So
this is exactly going to introduce us to what are the ways
those categories are defined and what are the special הלכות halachos attached
to each category.
Not only that you'd either pay full or be half, often times
yeah, who knows? Exactly. Let's take a look.
So now now we got the setup. תנו רבנן. Tenu Rabbanan. Okay,
so our Rabbis taught here the ברייתא braisa that's going to get
us into the answer. ג' אבות נאמרו בשור. Gimmel avos neemru beshor.
So forget the four אבות avos in the משנה, mishna, within שור
shor itself, שור shor breaks down into three אבות: avos: הקרן והשן
והרגל. hakeren vehashein veharegel. The horn, the tooth, and the leg. קרן
מנלן? Keren minalan? Where's the idea of the horn, the goring? תנו
רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: כי יגח, ki yigach, if a שור shor gores,
אין נגיחה אלא בקרן, ein negichah ela b'keren, that means with the
horn, שנאמר: shene'emar: ויעש לו צדקיה בן כנענה קרני ברזל. Vaya'as lo
Tzidkiyah ben Kena'anah karnei barzel. So Tzidkiyah made these horns of the
out of iron as they of a way of of like what
do you call it? Of like to symbolize a future prophecy, ויאמר
כה אמר ה' באלה תנגח את ארם, Vayomer koh amar Hashem b'eileh
tinagach et Aram, with these you will gore Aram. Okay, so you
see it speaks about a horn and being נוגח, noge'ach, goring. Wait,
I mean, this is from נביא Navi anyway, that's what I'm saying.
Right. ואומר: Ve'omer: בכור שורו הדר לו, bechor shoro hadar lo, the
firstborn of his ox is a glory to him, וקרני ראם קרניו,
vekarnei re'em karnav, the horns of a ראם, re'em, some people think
that means a unicorn, over then it wouldn't be in plural. Anyway,
the horns of whatever this animal is are his horns, בהם עמים
ינגח, bahem amim yenagach, with them he will gore nations. So it
talks about horns and goring. This is from before תורה. Torah. I
know. מאי ואומר? Mai ve'omer? Why did you have second פסוק? pasuk?
וכי תימא דברי תורה מדברי קבלה לא ילפינן? V'chi teima divrei Torah
mi-divrei kabbalah lo yalfinan? Ah, because we can't learn a תורה Torah
from from the words of the קבלה, kabbalah, which here does not
mean the Zohar, it means the נביאים. Nevi'im. Okay? So therefore, תא
שמע, ta shema, we'll learn
it from a פסוק pasuk in the תורה: Torah: בכור שורו הדר
לו. bechor shoro hadar lo.
So the גמרא Gemara says אי למלף aimalef or what?
We're not learning a law from
a פסוק pasuk there in מלכים. Melachim. So גילוי מילתא בעלמא הוא
דנגיחה בקרן, gilluy milta b'alma hu d'negichah b'keren, it's just showing us
what a word means. When the תורה Torah says כי יגח, ki
yigach, the פסוק pasuk in מלכים Melachim is not telling us, oh,
here's a הלכה halacha about a goring ox.
Okay, we just infer from that what the
term in the תורה Torah means. It's just learning out the meaning
of a word. It's a dictionary! Right, that's not הלכה halacha that
you can't learn from later in תנ"ך. Tanach. So the גמרא Gemara
says, so why still why do you need the פסוק pasuk in
the תורה? Torah? אלא מהו דתימא, Ella mahu d'teima, what would I
have thought? כי פלג רחמנא בין תם למועד. Ki palig Rachmana bein
tam l'mu'ad. Ah, maybe I would have said this because the basic
idea of קרן keren is the first three times the animal is
a תם, tam, is a like is a you know, is a
non is a you know, is a non innocent, non-repeat offender, I
guess is a funny way, innocent, non-repeat offender, and therefore it only
pays half. And מועד mu'ad is a habituated repeat offender, pays full.
So when does the תורה Torah make this distinction? הני מילי בתלושה.
Hanei milei bi-tlushah. Maybe that would be if it was a נגיחה
negichah like the case of נגיחה negichah in that פסוק pasuk in
מלכים. Melachim. The נגיחה negichah in מלכים, Melachim, he made these horns,
like these iron horns, it wasn't attached to the animal's head. So
maybe the נגיחה negichah of the תורה Torah would be if an
animal picks up an iron horn that was dropped by Tzidkiyah and
he puts it in his mouth and he gores with it. That
is completely bizarre and you only pay half. But if he gores
with his attached horns, maybe you pay full. Okay. So הני מילי
בתלושה, Hanei milei bi-tlushah, that's if he uses an attached horn. אבל
במחוברת, Aval bi-mechuberet, if it's a natural horn, אימא כולו מועד הוא,
eima kulo mu'ad hu, maybe it would always be considered habitual and
therefore you'd always pay full. So the פסוק pasuk by מלכים Melachim
is very explicit that it focuses on a horn and goring. Okay,
but nevertheless it's a detached horn. It's not exactly our case. So
תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear, בכור שורו הדר לו. bechor
shoro hadar lo. I don't know why he didn't start with the
פסוק. pasuk. I'm not going to get worked up over this. Yes.
So just this is a usage of תא שמע, ta shema, like
normally when I hear תא שמע, ta shema, I think it is
coming to dis—there's a controversy or there's a מחלוקת machlokeit and the
תא שמע ta shema is coming to offer a clarification. A clarification
and the structure is like question, תא שמע ta shema blah blah
blah, שמע מינה shema mina answer. And so here the structure is
very different. It's just like oh. Yeah, that's true. I mean, I'd
have to see how it plays out when the גמרא's Gemara doing
it in the context of like מדרש הלכה midrash halacha as opposed
to raising it as a הלכתי halachic question. But you're right, here
it means I would have had this ambiguity, the פסוק pasuk comes
and resolves the ambiguity. Exactly, yeah. Well, or at least it lacks
the שמע מינה shema mina at the end. תא שמע Ta shema
brings the text and then the שמע מינה shema mina says okay
now we've resolved it. But here we knew the answer at the
beginning, you know what I'm saying? But yeah, it is true, it's
used a little bit differently, yeah. I'm just looking at the note
over here. They asked this question today, they asked. Yeah, go ahead,
I'm really not interested in the answer, but go ahead. No, if
they didn't have the first one, they would have thought that that
was so unusual but would exempt entirely. Okay, there you go. All
right, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: תולדה דקרן מאי
היא? Toldah d'keren mai hi? Good, we've got the idea of the
אב, av, meaning the אב av like we sort of sum up
by שבת, Shabbat, by שבת Shabbat was the משכן, Mishkan, here the
אב av clearly is the case described in the תורה. Torah. So
the תורה Torah describes the case of goring, but let's identify what
type of goring, so we'll just be able to be concretely understand
what is the case in the תורה. Torah. The case in the
תורה Torah is goring with... Horns. That's the case. What would a
תולדה toladah be? Something that we'd put in the same category but
isn't the exact same concrete case. So, תולדה דקרן מאי היא? toladah
d'keren mai hee? What is it? נגיפה. negifah. Let's say it pushes
somebody. Okay, נשיכה neshichah bites somebody. רביצה revitzah well, the question is
why is it doing it? We're going to get to it. Crouches
on something and breaks it. בעיטה beitah kicks something. So the גמרא
Gemara says before we get to why those are
תולדות, tolados, we're first going to clarify the word נגיפה. negifah.
מאי שנא נגיפה דקרי ליה אב? mai shna negifah d'kari lei av?
You're right, you call נגיפה negifah an אב av because it says
it in the תורה, Torah, דכתיב כי יגח. d'chsiv ki yigach. Right?
That's the category. An אב av is the case in the תורה.
Torah. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says נגיפה נמי כתיב? negifah nami
ksiv? It also says נגיפה negifah in the תורה, Torah, which means
like pushing. כי יגוף שור איש את שור רעהו. ki yigof shor
ish es shor re'eihu. So the גמרא Gemara says no. האי נגיפה
נגיחה היא. hai negifah negichah hee. That נגיפה negifah in the פסוק
posuk is not the same as the נגיפה negifah in the ברייתא.
braisa. נגיפה negifah in the ברייתא braisa means to shove and to
push. That word נגיפה negifah in the פסוק posuk is another word
for goring. How do I know it's another word for goring in
the פסוק? posuk? דתניא פתח בנגיפה וסיים בנגיחה. d'tanya pasach b'negifah v'siyem
b'negichah. The פסוק posuk says כי יגוף שור איש את שור רעהו
ומת, ki yigof shor ish es shor re'eihu vamet, right? Then it
tells whatever. And then it says או כי נודע כי שור נגח
הוא מתמול שלשום. o ki noda ki shor nagach hu mitmol shilshom.
רש"י Rashi says it. או כי נודע כי שור נגח הוא מתמול
שלשום ולא ישמרנו בעליו, o ki noda ki shor nagach hu mitmol
shilshom v'lo yishmerenu ba'alav, right? So it starts by talking about pushing,
and then it's excuse me, uses the word נגיפה, negifah, but then
it says or it's gored multiple times, which presumably tells you that
the initial word meant goring. Okay, so yes, נגיפה negifah in the
ברייתא braisa means pushing, but in the תורה Torah clearly it means
goring. Okay, פתח הכתוב בנגיפה וסיים בנגיחה לומר לך זו היא נגיפה
זו היא נגיחה. pasach haksiv b'negifah v'siyem b'negichah lomar lach zo hee
negifah zo hee negichah. That means goring in the תורה. Torah. Now,
if that's true, why is the תורה Torah using different words? Why
does it sometimes use one and sometimes use the other? And in
particular what the גמרא Gemara notices is that when it speaks about
animals the word נגיפה negifah only occurs when it's talking about goring
animals. By animals it uses both the word נגיפה negifah and נגיחה.
negichah. By humans it only uses the word נגיחה. negichah. So it
thinks maybe that can tell us if they all essentially mean the
same thing, why maybe what's the nuance difference of why it uses
the word נגיפה negifah with animals and and by humans it exclusively
uses the word נגיחה? negichah? When it doesn't what? No, no, when
it does it to an animal as opposed to doing it to
I'm sorry if I wasn't clear. When an ox gores an ox,
it uses the word both נגיפה negifah and נגיחה. negichah. When the
ox gores a human, it only uses the word נגיחה. negichah. Okay,
so מאי שנא גבי אדם דכתיב כי יגח mai shna gabi adam
d'chsiv ki yigach only, only uses the word נגיחה. negichah. ומאי שנא
גבי בהמה דכתיב כי יגוף. u'mai shna gabi beheimah d'chsiv ki yigof.
By when it gores an animal it either says כי יגוף ki
yigof or יגח, yigach, but it also uses the word כי יגוף
ki yigof by goring animals. So the גמרא Gemara says like this:
אדם דאית ליה מזלא. adam d'is lei mazla. A human being that
has luck, okay, that maybe, you know, is more naturally protected from
injury because of the cosmos, however you explain what מזל mazel is.
Maybe personal? Maybe we yeah, you could obviously explain it in like,
you know, naturalistic terms. I don't know if that's the גמרא, Gemara,
but like, you know, we we more take care of ourselves if
you want to say that. Although I will tell you, I was
once on vacation somewhere, and, you know, we I was doing some
horseback riding and then we saw some people on these like, you
know, buggies, right, you know, these like these jeep buggies, whatever. And
I said, oh, that looks like that would be a lot of
fun, whatever. And this woman who was on their horseback riding said
to me, like, I would never go on a buggy rather than
a horse. I said, what are you talking about? Why? She said,
because you can drive a buggy off a cliff. You cannot get
a horse to ride off a cliff. Anyway, so it's interesting about
אית ליה מזלא, is lei mazla, לית ליה מזלא. lais lei mazla.
You know, it's like stupid acts of human beings. Anyway, okay, so,
אדם דאית ליה מזלא כתיב כי יגח. adam d'is lei mazla ksiv
ki yigach. Somehow human beings are less more protected by their own
wits or by cosmos. So therefore you need a it only יגח
yigach indicates like a very focused act of goring. Only then will
a human being get injured. בהמה דלית לה מזלא. beheimah d'lais lah
mazla. Animals that don't have that type of luck, כתיב כי יגוף.
ksiv ki yigof. It might happen with less intention. So what is
exactly the nuance difference? רש"י Rashi gives two explanations. One is יגוף
yigof might imply more a a more a crime of opportunity than
a crime of of then like you know, that an animal sees
another animal, it wasn't planning on goring it, but it happened by
another animal. Whereas by a human being, right, it will really only
if the ox is really dead set on doing it will it
happen, okay? So that's the difference between כי יגוף ki yigof and
כי יגח. ki yigach. The other difference רש"י Rashi just says is
with more is with more viciousness or power. כי יגוף ki yigof
is like a slight pushing. So a slight pushing might injure a
slight goring. might injure an animal when it wouldn't injure a human.
A human might require, you know, a more vicious type of נגח.
negach. So either more intentional or more vicious. Either way, fine. Now
why do we care about that? That's all very fascinating. What difference
does it make להלכה? le'halacha? So the גמרא Gemara says like this:
ומילתא אגב אורחיה קמשמע לן. u'milta agav urchia kamashma lan. So by
making these distinctions, you can actually learn out in passing a certain
halakhic issue. What can you learn out halakhically? דמועד לאדם הוי מועד
לבהמה ומועד לבהמה לא הוי מועד לאדם. de'muad l'adam havei muad l'behema
u'muad l'behema lo havei muad l'adam. If an animal is habitual of
goring a human being, then we know that it's a danger to
animals as well, okay, because it's got that viciousness or intention, it
will certainly be a danger to animals. But if an animal is
a habitual gorer of other animals, it cannot be assumed to be
a habitual gorer of humans, right? Animals are easier to gore, not
a whatever. So therefore, if it gores animals three times and then
it gores an animal a fourth time, it'll pay a full, the
owner will pay full. But if it gores a human after goring
an animal three times, it's still going to pay half. Because being
habitual for goring animals does not make it habitual for goring humans.
Okay, so now we've understood that the פסוקים psukim are talking about
goring, goring with a horn. That's the אב. av. What are the
תולדות? toldot? Does goring a person sort of take it out of
the category of being a vicious gorer, like? No, if it gores
a person three times, then it is habitual. No, gored an animal
two times and then- that's a separate conversation. We have a whole
פרק perek devoted to that. That's not what I'm saying. If it
gored three animals, it's not assumed to be habitual for humans. If
it gored three humans, it's habitual for animals. What about mixing and
whatever? Whatever, it's obviously more complicated than that, but that's the general
rule. Does that mean goring goring or killing people? Both. I'm not
getting into those distinctions. Does it have to be three? No. So
it is true. The תורה Torah describes the case where an ox
gored three times and what's the- and killed three times and then
it gored a fourth and the question is, how did it get
around to goring three times? You were supposed to kill it after
the third. So the point is, yeah, you never got around to
bringing it to בית דין Beis Din before it had done all
of these acts, okay? All of these things will be discussed. I'm
glad you're asking all the right questions. We have six פרקים prakim
to figure out the answers. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. The גמרא Gemara says like this, okay. Now, okay. Now,
now, so נגיפה negifa is pushing. Now, נשיכה, neshika, biting, the גמרא
Gemara says תולדה דשן הוא. toldah d'shein hu. That's like an act
of the tooth because the גמרא Gemara thinks that what defines the
category is which body part is used, okay? So anything using the
mouth, that's a שן. shein. The גמרא Gemara says no, no, no,
לא, שן יש הנאה להיזקא. lo, shein yesh hana'ah l'hezeika. This is
the first key shift definition the תורה Torah says. We are not
talking about body parts. We are not talking about oxen or body
parts. I don't care if it's your ox or your or your
dog or your bee or your you know whatever. We are not
talking about which part of the body. We are talking about the
nature of the act. The nature of the act of שן shein
is an act that is the reason the animal did it was
for its own pleasure and benefit, okay? It wanted to get some
physical pleasure. So we're going to say an act of שן shein
is it rubs its body against the wall to scratch its body
and the wall falls down, okay? That's just an act of being
focused on getting physical pleasure of the animal and damage occurred incidentally.
That's what שן shein means. That's what eating means. הא אין הנאה
להיזקא. ha ein hana'ah l'hezeika. In this case, when it bites someone,
it's not biting to eat. It's biting as an act of of
attack, right? So goring does not mean using the horn. Goring means
doing an act of intended violence against something, an act of attack.
And that's phrased as the גמרא Gemara hasn't used the phrase the
word right now, but that's called כוונתו להזיק. kavanaso l'hazik. Its intention
is to do damage. Okay, eating and trampling it's not intending to
do damage. Okay, רביצה, revitza, so the גמרא Gemara is going to
now just repeat this idea. רביצה ובעיטה, revitza u've'ita, kicking and crouching,
תולדה דרגל הוא, toldah d'regel hu, that's using the legs, that should
be רגל. regel. It says לא, רגל היזיקא מצוי, הני אין היזיקא
מצוי. lo, regel hezeika matzui, hanei ein hezeika matzui. So רגל regel
is it's doing a regular act of walking. Now, it's not really
walk- meaning רגל regel is שן shein as I says an act
of pleasure. When an animal sits down, it's not like about getting
physical pleasure, right? When an animal- what was the other one that
it said here in addition? רביצה. revitza. What, oh, that's kick- oh
sorry. But anyway, an act of רגל regel is an act of
the normal types of movement of an animal. So שן shein and
רגל regel are often categorized together because they're neither done with an
intention of doing damage. שן shein is done with a desire for
the animal to get physical pleasure and רגל regel is just the
normal type of movement of an animal. So if an animal talk
about pushing, if an animal accidentally pushed something over, that's רגל. regel.
If an animal pushes like this, you know, you can push someone
in line, right? That's קרן. keren. It doesn't matter everybody get it,
it does not matter the physical body part, right? An animal walking
and bumping into something is רגל, regel, an animal pushing something intentionally
is an act of קרן. keren. Okay. So these is, and in
these like two lines, we basically have the conceptual definition of קרן,
Keren, שן, Shen, and רגל. Regel. קרן Keren is כוונה להזיק, Kavanat
Lehazik, שן Shen is הנאה להזיקו, Hana'ah Leheziko, רגל Regel is היזקו
מצוי Hezeko Matsui which is not the best you know definition, it
really means something that happens incidentally through its natural type of movement.
Now Jacob, you have a question? What was the תורה Torah paradigmatic
רגל? Regel? We haven't got to that yet, we're going to get
there. Now the interesting question which I'll let us think about is
what happens when something falls into multiple categories? Right, you know in
like could you imagine something that had multiple of those characteristics and
then which category would it fall? Anyway, so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this, I'll let us read one more line, אלא תולדותיהן
לאו כיוצא בהן דאמר רב פפא אהיי. Ella toledoteihen lav keyotzei vahen
de'amar Rav Pappa ahai. So when רב פפא Rav Pappa says the
תולדות Toledot are not like the אבות, Avot, could which is it
referring to? אילימא הני, Eileima hani, if it's on the things we
just dealt with, the תולדה Toledah of a קרן, Keren, מאי שנא
קרן דכוונתו להזיק Mai shena Keren dechavanato lehazik and now that's the
third definition, הנאה להזיקו, Hana'ah leheziko, היזקו מצוי, Hezeko matsui, right? That's
שן Shen and רגל. Regel. And now we've given the definition to
קרן, Keren, כוונתו להזיק. Kavanato lehazik. So in these like three lines,
we gave a very precise conceptual definition. מאי שנא קרן דכוונתו להזיק,
Mai shena Keren dechavanato lehazik, it's intending to do damage וממונך ושמירתן
עליך. umamoncha ushmiratan alecha. Now borrowing the language of the משנה, Mishna,
it's your property and you have an obligation to watch it. הני
נמי כוונתו להזיק וממונך ושמירתן עליך. Hani nami kavanato lehazik umamoncha ushmiratan
alecha. So the other things in the category are the exact same.
Biting, kicking, they also are intending to do damage and it's your
money and you have an obligation to watch it. אלא Ella says
the גמרא Gemara you're right. תולדה דקרן כקרן. Toledah deKeren keKeren. The
תולדה Toledah of קרן Keren is like קרן. Keren. וכי קאמר רב
פפא Vechi kamar Rav Pappa when רב פפא Rav Pappa said the
תולדות Toledot are not like the אבות, Avot, אשן ורגל. aShen veRegel.
It's by שן Shen and רגל Regel and tomorrow we'll look at
שן Shen and רגל Regel and see are the תולדות Toledot like
it or not like it. But the last thing I want to
say is and this goes back to Dov's question earlier, that is
not the גמרא Gemara did say said the wrong thing. When the
גמרא Gemara wanted to say that the תולדות Toledot of קרן Keren
were like קרן, Keren, it should have said the same way the
אב Av you pay חצי נזק Chatzi Nezek the first three times
and a full נזק Nezek afterwards, the תולדות Toledot also you pay
חצי נזק Chatzi Nezek the
first three and the full afterwards. By saying the same way the
אב Av is כוונתו להזיק, Kavanato lehazik, the תולדות Toledot are כוונתו
להזיק, Kavanato lehazik, all you've told me is why did you put
it in the same category? You didn't tell me whether
it has the same הלכה Halacha or not. So it's a funny
phrasing of the גמרא. Gemara. But we'll assume that's what it means.
What we've now identified conceptually what are the categories: כוונתו להזיק, Kavanato
lehazik, דרכו להזיק, Darko lehazik, and הנאה להזיקו. Hana'ah leheziko. And we
now are going to start putting the different types of acts into
those conceptual categories, okay? And we will pick up with this.